for AI agents with terminal by
definition you can run the cloud codeex
gemini CLI in the non-interactive mode
just for a CLI given a prompt what you
want from this agent but I think
nowadays actually like any AI assistant
tools like such as Corser they are also
moving in this direction and they are
adding more and more capabilities I
think the interaction when you're
building an app in base 44 versus for
example load code or cursor it's a
different interaction base 44's users do
iterations and experimentation has a lot
to do with visual and this set is going
to expand further and further and
further as time goes.
>> What makes 2025 the year of Agentics is
this idea of recursion. These are agents
that could run for hours or days at a
time, but the costs were prohibitively
expensive. So in April of this year,
what we saw was Anthropic and Claude
Code came out and they started offering
a sort of unlimited all you could eat
buffet which allowed for that recursion.
And suddenly we were able to spawn these
swarms that could run for hours on end
and cost a flat fee.
[music]
Before we jump into this episode, I
wanted to let you know that this podcast
is for developers building with AI at
the core. So whether that's exploring
the latest tools, the workflows, or the
best practices, this podcast's for you.
A really quick ask, 90% of people who
are listening to this haven't yet
subscribed. So if this content has
helped you build smarter, hit that
subscribe button and maybe a like. All
right, back to the episode. Let's go
into agents a little bit uh deeper in
terms of the way we use them. Um you
mentioned cursor, you mentioned cord
code, very different usage patterns in
terms of one uses a terminal UI, one
uses a more classical IDE. Uh if we look
at others, in fact quite a few have
almost favored either IDE or terminal,
but there are a surprising number that
favor Terminal these days. Is there a
best way to use an agent? Uh is there a
way that is, you know, easier for us to
give an agent information or context or
is it really up to the user depending on
how the user prefers to interact with
that agent?
>> Yeah. So I think uh the interactivity is
the differentiator factor like when
you're using an ID with a extension uh
like a corser uh being like visible to
you then you are uh like agreeing to to
the scenario where you are in the loop
you are always checking what happens and
you are just doing this interactively.
So UI elements like simplifies uh and uh
um you know like accelerates the on
boarding um for you as a developer. It
doesn't replace you as a developer. It
just like here on the side exist to help
you with achieving like specific tasks
like executing uh helping you to write a
specific code file or specific unit
tests and so on and be very uh helpful
in the sense that there is a UI. you
don't need to know any commands because
there are buttons and uh it's just like
a box for you to type the text and
execute. So um I think like the cool uh
part of the cursor or windsurf is that
they are giving you this IDE uh with um
with lots of UI elements to help you uh
on board to using these tools more like
proactively and in your everyday use
case. While for AI agents like with
terminal by definition like you don't
need like uh buttons right uh like
complex things complex things can be
done just with a combination of the of
the of the of the keys uh or the
commands. So terminal is like for more
advanced users uh for those who are
ready to accelerate even further because
they don't need to have have
visualization. they are okay just like
leaving in the terminal and manipulating
[clears throat] all the commands in the
terminal because if you're at some point
advanced the Vimh or Nana or whatever
editor uh or a Git you actually don't
need UIs right you can just do and
achieve very hard scenarios with
terminal directly and it saves you time
but again like it's just like a bit
harder because it's less interactive
because it's easier to to lose what
happens um and I think the the amount
amount of the generated information
sometimes may be overwhelming. So it's
hard to navigate through the terminal
just because there's so many things are
happening and it requires some skill to
learn how to use it properly.
>> Yeah, absolutely. And I think things
like cursor for example where you see
the the the changes and you can flick
from file to file very very easily. You
obviously miss that from the from the
terminal point of view. But I don't know
what it is about you know just being a
terminal that actually just makes me
feel faster, more productive at the
terminal. Um, and of course when you're
at the terminal, you get the power of
the terminal, right? It's it's it tell
us a little bit about how you can
effectively use the terminal beyond just
cloud code.
>> Yeah, that's true. And another super
advantage of the terminal solution is
that like uh it gives you a batteries to
run your agent uh in the background,
right? like you can run the cloud codeex
gemini CLI in the non-interactive mode
um just for a CLI given a prompt what
you want to you know what you want from
this agent to to do and it will spawn in
a background process and fully on its
own start executing uh this complex
request which you ask it but I think
nowadays actually like any AI assistant
tools like such as uh Corser they are
also moving in this direction and
they're adding more and more
capabilities for example A couple of
months ago, Corsor couldn't u have
access to a terminal. So you if you run
something, you need to you needed to
copy and paste directly in the uh in the
text box uh of the of the cursor the
error message for example but now it
actually has access to a terminal. So it
has access to the information which you
are in a terminal like uh using so
that's one thing. and others that Corser
also launched their own agent which can
be also non-interactive or CLI. So they
are covering this space as well. Uh you
know they want to get both sides and
both people like who are who want to
inter who want to have more
interactivity and who who are okay to uh
work just with CLI.
>> It's funny how I think we're fairly
familiar you and I with trying out a
bunch of these and I think everything
that we've mentioned so far I've
definitely played with. I'm sure you
have and there's obviously a bunch of
others. Gemini CLI, I think you actually
maybe mentioned Gemini, Codeex is
another. Where would you say like for
for those listening who are kind of like
on the you know trying to trying to
follow this 101 working out well where
do I actually start? Where would you say
is like a good place to start? Is there
is there one good place or is it really
depending on where where a user is most
consistently,
>> you know, doing those tasks? Is it
better they try and find an agent in
that environment? What would you
recommend?
>> I think it depends on the level of
experience and maybe on the role of the
person in the company if we're talking
about some some technical people because
definitely there are no code solutions
right uh like lovable for example that
gen that provides you a uh vibe coding
platform for developing back ends and
front ends uh instantly without any
knowledge of the code. So it requires
you zero knowledge. it just requires you
to be there to validate and approve the
the the content generated by the AI um
assistant or whatever. Uh and the more
the closer you are to the code uh and
the more scale you need uh then the more
advanced tools you need to use um which
require potentially a lot of manual
resolution uh of the problems. So for
example, if you're like a software
engineer and you are writing and your
your goal is to develop a lot of
software tasks and uh a lot of
manipulations with the code, then you're
okay to start with first of all a
copilot just to see if you're if the
copilot models are helping you to at
least accelerate your productivity uh as
a as a developer. So does it help you to
write a better faster code? If you're
happy with the copilots, then you're
going to the next extension and go with
a corser ID uh when you're starting
using these complex assistants uh as
your companions helping you achieving
the task. And now the scope uh of
autonom autonomy and what assistants can
do grows. So you can delegate it to
change not just a function but entire
files. And once you're okay with that
then you can can move to the top of this
hierarchy and start using cloud code and
corsor or gemini cla um directly in the
terminal because now you know the strong
sides of this now you know what you can
delegated it and probably already like
familiar with core capabilities and
familiar with how this uh tools are
working so you can delegate even more
scope uh in a fully autonomous pipeline
or setup. So I think the the the
reasoning should be like that. Um start
with something super simple which
doesn't require any knowledge of code
and if you already have a knowledge then
progress further uh and go into more and
more advanced uh tools.
>> I think it's a really really good advice
in terms of it's not just actually about
well there's two things I think here.
One one is that there's a trust
implication and it's important to be in
control like when we start learning how
to drive. We don't jump into a Ferrari
and try and try and try and drive that
Ferrari. It's about do, you know, taking
small steps. Once we're comfortable with
it, once we trust ourselves as well as
the tools that we have, we go on to the
next step. And and this growth in
autonomy is is all about that growth in
trust. I I absolutely love that. And I
and I like the the focus there as well
in terms of you know sticking to where
you're most familiar in that sense of if
you're if you're familiar with an IDE
well maybe let's let's start you know
[clears throat] when you go from there
maybe GitHub copilot or something about
in the ID is the best place and then
maybe cursor if you want to stay with
IDE if you love terminals maybe dip into
something else from from from that
really really like that advice some some
of our listeners may have heard of sub
aents before what's the difference
between an agent and a sub agent
>> some like sub agents is basically an
instance
uh like another instance of an agent
just spawned and controlled by the main
agent and you usually use that when your
task is so complex that one agent is not
enough to tackle it and when there are
different options or different paths
that can be explored. Uh so I think like
yeah two two scenarios where the the
problem is so complex that it needs to
be split into smaller parts or when you
need to make a search to like just
explore the space and uh choose one one
of the options. So yeah these two
scenarios but basically sub agent is
just like another instance of uh of a
main agent which is asked to solve a
specific problem. So uh you can think of
it as a master slave architecture uh
right like if you are for example
interacting with a master agent with
with the one which is you have access in
your terminal uh and you ask it to
develop a um a service that has a front
end and a back end then it's a great
candidate for splitting uh and spawning
a sub agents. One sub agent will be
working on the back end, another agent
will be working on the front end. Um,
and they will be doing their like pieces
independently and then at some point
they will go back to the master uh agent
to communicate back the result and the
ma master will decide are they okay or
like is the result is fine? Does it
satisfy the overall goal? And if not
then it will circle back the the
information to them and give a feedback
and they like continue iterating or
refining uh based on the feedback which
they receive to improve this back end
and front end. That's a uh example of
how to use sub aents for coding
assistance for tasks beyond coding where
you need like exploration. Uh sub agents
might be just like a parallel instances
of the same agent which are just
exploring the problem from different
angles. For example, you want to search
uh for some information like to answer
some specific question and then you can
make a search with one type of query in
the Google. You can make a search over
the articles in the Wikipedia. You can
do a search over the information
available in your I don't know like
local database and for all that
scenarios they all about the search uh
of the information in different sources
but they are done by just like a
different agents. Technically speaking,
uh in in some future there won't be need
uh in sub agents because the master
agent will be so smart and will be
knowing how to um how to resolve any
challenging problem uh on its own. So it
won't it won't you know lose and won't
forget about the context. It will know
how to navigate in this complex
structure on its own and technically it
won't need to have spawning sub aents.
Um but another reason for another
motivation for the sub agents is just
like speed. All we we know that agents
are super slow. If you try to paralyze
them and sub a is one way of doing this,
you just get a result faster. You just
get like 10 implementations of the same
thing and maybe one or two of them are
good and working and doing what you
expecting. So it's just like um like you
know like latency um and throughput
uh versus idling time. Um yeah,
>> I think like the time that you mentioned
there and the parallelization as well as
the context are both really good reasons
to use them. Um in terms of in terms of
the cons the the the the negatives that
that they can that they provide. Is it
just is it like burning tokens more or
anything anything that we need to be
cautious of?
>> Yeah, I mean like for sure like costs
will grow uh linearly, right? like with
more agents you will cost like spend
more. Um and sometimes there might be a
situation where you like again like
spawn the these old agents but they
actually didn't converge to anything. Um
and another disadvantage is that there
are different ways how to spawn how to
launch the sub agents. One is that your
main agent can launch uh sub agents on
its own because like cloud code actually
now gives this capability. You can ask
explicitly saying explicitly in the
prompt use parallel agents to analyze
this complex document. Right? So you can
explicitly state it in the prompt and it
will on its own spawn like multiple
versions of the agents. But the thing is
is that you can you might want to have
specialized sub sub aents, right? So
instead of like general search sub
agents, you want to have sub aents
focused on a specific access or a
specific angle of a problem. And here
you need like to have extra
customization you need to work you need
to uh carefully design instructions for
uh for that sub agent in order to get
the best you know get get great result.
So the downside that you know like
speaking of downsides the time for
designing these sub aents it's also like
uh an art and you need to make an
effort. If you don't do it then probably
um main agent will do it on its own but
the quality of the sub agents might be
different because it might just like
miss uh some some some important bits uh
in in in the structure to the sub agent.
>> Yeah. and and in terms of the agents
like other other than being able to
customize an agent and be able to a sub
agent rather and and be able to say,
"Hey, I want you to use this sub agent
when you're when you're doing these
types of things." Uh or or allow it to
choose the the the appropriate kind of
sub agents to do those tasks. I presume
the main agent is the is pretty much
entirely the the the communicator across
sub agents. There's no human interaction
between uh that that bypasses the main
agent.
>> Yeah. I mean like it depends on the
design of your system and I think in
close code it's very hard to control it
like usually the sub agents are launched
on the background so you don't actually
have access directly to see what they
are doing you only can see it in the
logs so if you open the um code uh JSONL
file to see what were the commands you
will see that agents was doing something
on the background but you won't
necessarily see it in your terminal uh
you won't necessarily see the the
thinking process the the path the
planning for each of the sub agents. So
yeah, like again and maybe another like
I don't know disadvantage or even
advantage of this is that like you trust
it even more. So you need to believe in
in the fact that it will come up with
something uh meaningful even more if you
are entering the world of sub agent. If
you're uh a developer, I think a lot of
vibe coding, whether it is in platforms
like B 44 or if it's things that you do
more locally, the cloud code sort of
cursors of the world, um you in in those
worlds, you have a very tight
relationship to the code. The the LLM
modifies the agents modify the code, but
when there's a problem, your sort of
supervision happens on the code. I think
in B 44 you can see the code but it is
it is a kind of a hidden entity or it is
not it's not designed to put the code in
your face too much. How do you how have
you seen and what maybe there's like
learnings learnings about how you have
built for people who don't understand
code to be able
>> know to to interact and get the system
over the hump when it fails to deliver
something right when it fails to
accomplish something. Is it all just
like give it more guidance, give it more
guidance and and hope it gets it right?
>> Yeah. Um, not only I think the
interaction
when you're building an app in B 44
versus, for example, if you're building
an app using CL code or cursor, it's a
different interaction and and many times
it's a different user and a lot of times
currently it's a different piece of
software. So I'll start with obviously
the way that um P44's users do
iterations and experimentations and so
on has a lot to do with visual like you
see the app in front of your face. You
know if something is wrong you'll see
that in the interaction or you'll see a
bug being thrown away or something like
that before you even look at the code.
Um I think platforms like base 44 still
there's obviously like a limited set of
software that they can build. Um and
this this set is going to expand further
and further and further as time goes and
that's what we're working on. But it's
still important to be very honest and
say there's a set of software that
you'll be better off building using
cursor than than than using B 44. Um so
for example B 44 itself put aside the
front end which is obviously built using
B 44 but the back end for B 44 is not
built using B 44 it's like built using
cursor and CL code and so on
>> um because you need to look at the code
and you need to understand the code and
so
>> this whole thing like this is the
situation and reality right now I think
this is this will aggressively change in
the next few months even but definitely
few years again as as you'll be able to
visually or or like prompts only uh
without looking at the code, you'll be
able to build an increasing
percentage of the software that you're
currently building,
>> right?
>> Um and yeah, and so the tools that we're
giving our users are are a different set
of tools to how how they experiment and
iterate with our software. It has to do
a lot with visual. you have to see the
the the application all the time. It has
to do a lot with trying to explain
better what's going on. So for example,
we have this uh small feature, but
people really love it where when you
prompt something in B 44 and it starts
coding. So obviously we like most of our
users don't want to see the code. It's
just it's terrifying for them. So they
don't understand what's going on. And so
we have another small LLM
>> that basically watches the coding agent,
see what it does, and kind of like
explains to you in real time like what's
the coding agents currently doing. And
when it's like a small like now it's
changing the uh UI from light team to
dark theme and whatever. And so yeah,
we're building a set of tools to help
people build software without the need
to look at code.
>> Yeah. Yeah. That's so smart. progress
indications and uh and engagement are
sort of super important. So I think that
makes sense to me. If I echo this back,
I feel you're saying um there sort of
the two domains maybe that base 44 today
is most helpful are cases where a lot of
the validation and a lot of the
decisions are much more product oriented
and a lot more visual specifically
oriented uh and uh as opposed to sort of
technical and how did you implement and
the second is that maybe a lot of them
are are places where that visual is also
the innovation like a lot of the
technology you're not looking to uh make
a product that sort of works that's not
some sort of the world's fanciest
progressive web app that uh does a lot
of things. a lot of your your creation
is a lot more about the content uh and
the navigation and all that might be
sort of similar and common and so the
LLMs know how to do it well and you can
do it very efficiently but you're
innovating on sort of the the content
and the looks uh more uh is that does
that sound fair
>> and then it will expand over time
>> definitely but I'll add on top of that I
think it has more to do with the type of
software that you're building right so
>> if you're building nowadays is something
that that's like performance is super
important, right? Like you can't vibe
code your way through it. Like it's like
if you're building I don't know a VPN
software, let's take this for example.
Um
>> yeah,
>> so obviously like it's it's going to be
really hard or something that relies
very heavily on like back end and stuff
like that. So
>> the previous company probably can't vibe
code snake.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh at least not yet.
uh I think for other set of applications
it's not necessarily the visuals but
more of like if you're building an
application that that can do what it
needs to to do with a database a set of
integrations APIs and so on um I think
like you you'll be like you can do a
really good job using B 44 and it will
likely be an easier experience than try
to code it via cursor
>> right yeah
>> uh so it has to with like the
lowlevelness of stuff and complexity on
the back end side. Uh but we are getting
better at that.
>> So uh I have one more question on base
44 but maybe let's first switch to how
you built it. We'll talk about your
stack and then we'll combine a little
bit. I'd like to uh touch a bit on
longevity like building a disposable
app. I think you're creative doing it
versus what do you build for long term?
But take us behind the scenes a sec. So
you've built, you know, a single person
built some substantial platform and also
scaled it. Uh I guess tell tell us a bit
of the uh of the tips and tricks. I
heard you shared a few of you know what
what helped you uh create that and maybe
started with like do you think you could
have done this? I know you used AI your
creation like was that critical? Do you
feel you could have pulled off a base 44
without AI dev help uh as a builder? Uh
short answer is definitely not. I was at
least not in the same structure and way
that I did it with B 44. So when I
started B 44, even before knowing what I
was going to do, I knew that we're in a
different era. I've been like leveraging
AI, working with AI in my previous
company, both as like AI inside the
product and also coding with AI. Mhm.
>> Um and I felt like I felt strongly that
we're in a new era where doesn't matter
the number of people building software
anymore about like if you have a unique
take unique product kind like uh and you
can design well like design software
well not I'm not speaking about like UI
design
>> then it's not anymore about like hey
throw as many people at the problem as
you can those people will write more
code faster and that's where you'll get
So I was like I'm going to do this alone
from day one. I'm going to set up the
repository
and spend 20% of my time constantly
on how can I further uh increase the
velocity and speed. So a lot of what I
did is like experimentation with how LM
write uh code better. Obviously I did it
for base 44's product as well but but
even for my own repository right so I
find those tips and tricks is like what
I I've spoken about like JavaScript
versus TypeScript maybe now it's
changing with cloud for and so on but
back then it's like I could write
>> uh front ends like the speed of light uh
just because of the setup.
>> Mhm. Uh another thing is is I've built
this from the backend side. I built this
very high level
uh infrastructure
uh that handles like the database and
user management and so on. So that even
if I would have pivoted to a completely
different idea, 80% of the code would
stay the same. And so I had this like
really good infrastructure
um that stayed the same. And that's what
those were like the parts of code that
it was slightly more me than the AI
actually writing and making sure that
it's perfect and formed that once you
have those infrastructure and so now
adding a new feature that I don't know
has like a new table in a database and
has some integr some interaction with
with other parts of the platform became
super easy. Uh the way I would measure
that is for the LLM to implement a new
feature, I wanted to write at at the
least code possible to implement the
feature end to end. And so I built a lot
of like those things obviously and rules
and so on into the repository so that I
could run on my own but still keep the
same velocity as my competitors if not
even better faster. And I think I think
to some degree I've done that. Like I
think the the competitors in this
category are super heavily funded. Um
and in many ways and aspects base 44
executed
uh extremely fast if not faster than
than a lot of the players in the in the
category
>> and I give a lot of credit to the AI
like most of the credit is to to the AI
of like structuring it
>> for getting your uh the
>> Yeah, I want to thank it. [laughter]
It's like a NASCAR. I get the
>> I think uh so so so I love that. I guess
again kind of echoing back a little bit.
I think you know the first thing you're
sort of touting is like the value of a
good architecture uh where you
anticipate uh what would be future
changes and you write the ability to
write compartmentalized code and I guess
I'm I'm hearing something that is almost
similar like to hiring either junior
developers or outsourcing you know
places in which if you built the right
architecture [clears throat] then you
could have clear instructions to someone
else who's maybe a little bit less
trustworthy uh to write pieces of
software within it uh and be able to
assess whether they've done their job
well and be uh I guess can be able to to
guide them. Does that sound like a fair
analogy?
>> Yeah. Yeah. Exactly. Because also one
one other thing that like I've noticed
is like when you're leveraging AI for
coding so think about it this way like
you let's say you're building like a
simple
full stack web app, right? So uh you
tell hey I want it to be um a to-do list
app or whatever. So the AI implements
like some of the routes and connects the
front end and so on and then you open up
a new chat right in cursor or something
and you want to implement another
features like write an admin panel or so
on. Uh so it will look at your code and
it will do the task but and AI is really
good at that but AI is not really good
at stop and saying oh you know what
there's actually like common concepts
here that I could like combine to like
this infrastructure or package that I
can later use in other features and oh
I'm writing the same code again and
again like let's stop and before I do
like the the task that you gave me let's
kind of like implement
>> yeah let's refactor the code so I won't
need to write as much code and so on. So
I think this is something that a lot of
developers currently don't notice about
AI like it will it will implement the
task as you told it to
>> but it's still lacking the hey let's
stop for a second we need to refactor
the code because I find this common
layer or whatever and I think that's
that's
>> and so those that's something you still
did manually like you would observe what
the AI has built and you would kind of
go off and and modify it. A lot of a lot
of what we see with AI which I think
touches on the topic you said right now
is is about the initial creation right
and it would go off and even there you
sort of see this sort of reward seeking
right it might burn down the house to
sort of be able to accomplish this thing
that you've just like break all the
other features you know just to be able
to make this feature you just asked it
to to make it work but um but but the
other aspect is indeed maintainability
it's indeed code duplication it's all
these things that are sort of bad
practices
uh when it comes to sort of quality
software creation. Um, so I guess I'm
asking like I think you've you you did
it on your own in B 44 for your
codebase. How do you think about that in
terms of building applications
that are built by B 44
>> um to to have longevity? So in two ways,
one, when you build an app in B 44 these
days, like there's a lot of
infrastructure and setup that happens
before the LLM even writes code
>> that in some ways limits it, but not
really, not in terms of like what it
needs to, but it kind like it it those
are guard rails that the LLM should keep
>> and as long as it keeps that, then then
it should be fine to some degree. Um so
again we automatically create the entire
uh uh read update delete kind like the
CRUD SDK and and we make it like really
good and we implement like rate limits
on top of that and things like that that
LMS wouldn't really care about and when
you leverage
um I don't know APIs and integrations
and so on like we kept a very strict
schema there's like a lot of things that
we implement mented built into the
application so that LLM won't kind like
be this reward seeking of like I'll do
whatever but I'll I'll keep your app
exposed and and so on. The other the
other thing is yes at some points uh we
automatically feedback the LLM whether
the user knows about it or not that it
needs to refactor or something. So for
example uh one of the things that makes
LLM confused the most um and people feel
that like across the the the VIP coding
category is uh when they're saying like
hey I asked it to do something it didn't
do it it did the opposite it deleted a
feature or whatever um is when code
files are are getting too long uh right
>> right if if like you've implemented so
you ask it initially or early on, hey,
implement this page, create a to-do
list, and it did something simple. It's
like a very simple to-do list like in
any other React, and then you start
layering in features, right? So, the LM
does what what you asked it to, and and
it start adding like uh AI features to
write the task description and then user
management to like assign different
teams and boards and whatever. And at
some point, you have like if you're not
careful, you might have like this very
large code file. Right.
>> So, one of the things is like we're
running behind the scenes refactoring
tests uh to maybe tell the LLM, hey,
like you passed the threshold, you
should now refactor this file. Even if
like okay, the user ask you something,
first refactor the file, then implement
what the user has asked you to. And I
think like there's a lot more to do
there. But yeah, it's somewhat of like
this uh code quality agent that that's
keep nudging the LLM at some points if
it finds that it's past a threshold of
like hey like there's this code here and
this code here like do something
refactor that
>> what was the thing do you feel that
really kind of like allowed us to turn
agents on in our code generation? Is it
is it context? Is it trust from from
humans in the process? Is it the
capabilities of LLMs?
>> I don't think it's trust. I think anyone
that's building these systems inherently
doesn't trust the output and needs to
spend quite a bit of time verifying that
what it's actually given us is true and
valid and functional and not just a kind
of mock or simulated version of what we
asked it. So there's a tendency for the
system to to you know kind of take the
shortest path to give you the the the
outcome. So a lot of what an engineer is
doing is is is working with solid
structures, architectures and other
things to to sort of validate what's
being built is is just functionally true
and correct. Now to your question, what
makes 2025 the year of of sort of
agentics if if that's if that's even a
thing is
one of the big breakthroughs last year
was again this idea of recursion. So um
we a group of us we created these were
kind of systems that could operate on a
kind of long horizon. These are agents
that could run for for hours or days at
a at a time and and then eventually
complete whatever problem they they were
given. Now the drawback to that we could
run it for third I think I did a 36-hour
test mostly just to show that I could
run an agent you know for 36 hours but
the costs were prohibitively expensive.
And what we saw as we scaled these
agents is a lot of the to to effectively
run this, you're looking at even on a
minimal basis around $4,000
a day. And when we really cranked it up
to, you know, dozens of agents running
concurrently, we're looking at $7,500 US
an hour to run uh at at this at a 10
agent swarm concurrently, basically. And
the it's just it's substantially cheaper
to hire a person at that per at that
point to do that work. It's just even
though you could you could do a ton of
output, most applications didn't require
that level of of scale or capacity. So
in April of this year, what we saw was
uh Anthropic and Claude Code came out
and they started offering a sort of
unlimited all you could eat buffet for
for for tokens and capability. And the
first thing we did is we re sort of
imagined the previous iterations of the
what we call the spark protocol which
allowed for that recursion. And suddenly
we were able to to spawn these swarms
that could run for hours on end and cost
a flat fee often 20 starting at $20, you
know, for an entire month, which is went
from thousands of dollars to $20, you
know, thousands of dollars an hour to
$20 a month. So we saw this interesting
inflection of both capability. So
suddenly we we were able to build things
dramatically faster and more with a lot
more capability at an exponentially
lower cost which is an interesting sort
of you don't generally see that happen
all at once. And that was basically May.
>> Yeah. And that's super interesting
because I think is that both the making
it more affordable but also the
parallelization it really opens up uh
the the quality of what we can actually
get back as well as as a response. I
want to talk about that in just a
second. Before we move on to to swarms
and and and spark specifically um I'd
love to talk a little bit about the
foundation that you created the Agentics
Foundation. Um first of all the Agentics
Foundation isn't kind of like super new
I guess. tell us a little bit about what
um you know what the need was for that
foundation. What's what's the problem
it's trying to solve?
>> It's an it's an organic sort of
evolution of of the work. And I'm going
to tell you a little backstory which is
going to probably make me sound
absolutely crazy, but I'm going to say
it anyway. So, I was early in into Chat
GBT. I was lucky enough to be an early
beta tester. Uh, I think they called it
a VIP program back in in 2022 with
OpenAI. And you know, so I basically
means I got it maybe three or four weeks
before everybody else. And one of the
first things I asked it is is how can I
be, and this is going to sound really
egotistical, but how can I be the most
influential person in AI is what I asked
Chat GBTV1 pre-launch. And it and it
gave me this this sort of step-by-step
process that said, you know, first of
all, what are you good at? What do you
like? and what you know what where where
do you want to be in a few years and it
it suggested that anything worth doing
takes years of sort of prep and and you
know to get to that point and and it g
it set it gave me this outline based on
a kind of Q&A that you'd have with
chatgbt and most of you have ever used
chatbt and know know the kind of you
know asking open-ended question sort of
routine and it said basically you're
going to have to build a social media
following and you should be narrow in
that focus and and some I'm asking well
what does that actually mean. He says,
"Well, what do you like to do?" And I I
like to build autonomous things. I I've
been building cloud infrastructure for
nearly 25 years, that sort of thing. And
it set me down this path and and said,
"First of all, you need to create a a
subreddit." Now, I know nothing of
Reddit or subreddits, but I did it. I
followed the guidance and and, you know,
three and a half years later, I've got
100,000 plus subscribers of the
subreddit. I'm not really sure exactly
why or what I'm going to do with this
subreddit. It's it but it's popular. And
then it said I needed to do and and the
key was consistency. It said it it told
me that I needed to build a following by
constantly posting interesting things
that I'm doing and sharing those things
publicly on my GitHub, creating weekly
um you know live casts where I can
interact with people. I followed the
guidance and next thing you know I I I
have, you know, thousands and thousands
of people, you know, showing up for
these these live casts, following me and
and essentially buying my time on a kind
of only only fans for geeks sort of
approach where people can sort of
essentially buy my my time on an hourly
basis. And and it and the craziest part
of the whole story is it it actually
worked. And I now I I'm I'm I'm in a
fortunate position where I I can claim,
you know, more than 100 customers, 20
Fortune Fortune 500 clients. I'm
literally one guy, one company. Um you
know, a company of one and my my wife
actually helps with with some of the
non-technical parts, but generally
speaking, it's me and my bots. And the
entire sort of business plan and process
was literally set forth by ChatGpt V1,
which is in itself just amazing to me.
Did the LLM tell you to create the
foundation or was that something that
you've
>> The foundation was an evolution of those
early conversations? No, it did. It
didn't exactly say that. And what
happened was as the as the community
coalesed around the concepts of agentics
and the sort of practical approaches
that we were taking to implement the
agentic systems, it became pretty clear
that we were in the midst of a new
profession. And and when you look
historically at different professions
and and and maybe and and let me let me
be honest, AI gives you sort of you know
delusions of grandeur often but the in
this particular case there was a group
of us and we we're realizing that we are
all practicing a sort of similar
approach to the sort of engineering of
AI and and and when you when we looked
at it we saw a spectrum. We saw on one
end we had these vibe coders. These vibe
coders are not I'm not saying that vi
coding isn't important. It's a great
ideation, learning and discovery sort of
mechanism, but it's very free form. It's
very it's very fluid in in what you're
doing without really much of a plan. And
what we were doing was different. What
we were doing is creating architectures
and process and and approaches that were
repeatable with a defined outcome that
that was an engineering activity. And
what we saw was the the the term
agentics and agentic engineering was
starting to be co-opted by large
companies who were essentially kind of
AI washing the concept there. They were
saying it was an agent but it was a
chatbot or it was a vibe coding system.
And we saw this as an opportunity for us
to say well this is our approach. This
is what we believe an agentic engineer
as a professional or as a profession
should encompass both technically as
well as the sort of ideas of almost like
a like a guild but for our group of of
engineering right so we're the
stonemasons for this new emerging uh
field of of you know agentic engineering
for AI that and the group formed around
that it's open it's it's the sort of
antithesis of some of the corporate um
open groups open AI sort of being the
other end of the spectrum you know
dominated by corporate interests we said
we need to make this for people to sort
of empower them both professionally and
maybe there's some more aspirational but
as a as the society around AI takes
shape what does that actually look like
and how do we protect the interests of
the people ultimately that are going to
be affected by it most so we act we want
anyway to act as a kind of hedge against
trillion dollar companies um if we can
do that and that was formed in March of
this year and next thing you know we're
in something like 60 cities. We've got
event multiple events sort of organic
startups or you know meetups all around
the uh all around the world happening
every week
>> and people can just join that. How do
people what's the best way to people for
people to kind of like get involved?
>> Well, we've got a a lot of the communic
the the communication and community
happens around either our Discord
channel discord.agentics.org
or WhatsApp. Our WhatsApp's maxed out,
so I'm not going to give you the address
because, you know, when you hit the
certain threshold, you basically can't
add anybody. Um, but uh most of it we've
shifted to Discord at this point. And
Gentix.org, it's a again a member
organization, meritocracy if you will.
So the if you if you want to get
involved, you want to create a new
chapter in a different city, do a
meetup, basically you just volunteer, we
and we make it happen. So if we were to
look at the state of Agentic today, what
would you say are kind of the things
that are creating that ceiling for for
for Agentic today, what are what are the
biggest things that causing Agentic uh
development to to fail or at least to to
to cause problems to developers trying
to use Agentic development today?
>> The limiting factors of the space right
now. And there was an interesting report
from MIT a couple weeks ago, I think it
was, that basically said 95% of agentic
projects fail. And it was a a fair a
fairly sort of sensational title. And if
and when you when you dig into that a
little bit, there there's two ways to to
to think about those types of sort of
stats. one they you know 95% of projects
fail which is probably true but the
reason between but for that failure is
likely 99% of of engineers programmers
developers project managers don't know
how to actually build agentic systems
and it's a byproduct of a new emerging
space and it and it's so the the
limiting factor is the fact that it's
really hard to to look beyond this sort
of um a you know I call it AI washing
the agentic washing of products and the
and the people associated with it to
determine you know what the capabilities
of the products and the people
implementing these products really are.
So when you see this sort of high
failure rate, it speaks to the fact that
we're in a new emerging space. And when
you go, if you're old enough to have
been around at the beginning of the
internet, you would have seen the same
thing with a lot of the internet
projects that corporations took on back
in the late 90s. And there was this sort
of, you know, th this idea that the
internet wasn't quite going to cut it
for most business type applications. And
then they were wrong. It was the fact
that we didn't as a industry understand
exactly how to build userfriendly
internet-based applications and over
time there were models to follow
Amazon's and the eBays and whatnot
showed up and we're like okay this is
how you create a web-based service that
people can easily interact with and it's
not just recreating software same
problem 25 years later 30 years later in
the AI space there's a tendency for
people to build applications the way
they've always built them with with
human centric models, uh, review cycles,
long drawn out sprints, um, and
different sort of, you know, traditional
tactics that were optimized for a world
where we built slowly over time and
gradually. Now, we're in a world where
we can literally copy anything anywhere
at at a moment's notice. and the ability
the the quality of the code although
important is less important than the
momentum that you get in terms of speed
and time to market. So when you're
looking at companies that are embracing
this they're they're embracing this in a
way that doesn't just replace their
developers that that might be a
byproduct but it augments them in ways
that those developers were never able to
do before. So you're empowering them
with sort of a kind of superpower to to
to create much more effectively and much
more quickly which in itself creates a
whole variety of secondary problems. But
ultimately this is this is the
empowerment of developers to to do more
with less.